There's this hormone that is rarely
discussed. No, it's not insulin. It's
not cortisol. None of the typical
hormones that we discuss, but it's
produced by many cells of our body. And
there's a recent massive study that
implicates it in having many longevity
promoting effects in the body. So, I'd
like to show you some of wickedly
impressive science on how it works and
how we can take advantage of the science
to apply it to increase the hormone in
our own body naturally. So, no
injections, no drugs, not even a
supplement. Oh, before we get started,
I'm about to get into some heavy
molecular and cell biology and
physiology. So, if you're a person who
doesn't care about the details, just
want the overall conclusion, you can
skip to the main point section at the
end of this video. For my people, the
nerds, buckle in. Let's get going. The
hormone is FGF-21, also known as
fibroblast growth factor 21. And the
researchers from this study wanted to
investigate what FGF-21 does to the body
because there are several other studies
that individually point to it having a
longevity effect. So to investigate the
researchers did a series of experiments
in mice. Don't worry, there are studies
in humans too that we'll get into. In
mice, they were able to generate FGF-21
knockout mice as well as an inducible
FGF-21 expression. That means for the
FGF-21 knockout group, the researchers
knocked out or eliminated the ability
for the cells of the body to read or
express the FGF-21 gene. In this case,
we have the FGF-21 gene, and the
researchers have added a linear DNA
sequence that mimics the FGF-21 gene,
but it is missing a critical piece of
the gene that allows it to be recognized
by the gene reading machinery inside the
cells known as the RNA polymerase and
some other enzymes. So the cell
recognizing the fake FGF-21 gene will
integrate it into its DNA using its
natural mechanisms called homologous
recombination. Now in essence the cell
gets fooled into swapping out the
functional FGF-21 gene for the broken
one, disallowing FGF-21 from being
produced. Pretty freaking cool, right?
And as for the inducible FGF-21 group,
that's a group with an extra FGF-21
gene, but it's inducible, meaning that
it has a region on the gene that
activates it. Meaning that when the mice
are fed a particular inducible molecule,
in this case doxycyc, the molecule binds
that region of the gene and allows the
gene reading machinery to read and
produce the extra FGF-21. So naturally,
these mice produce more than normal.
Okay, I realize that was a lot, but it's
going to actually be important to
understand the experiments that we're
going over. Now, we have our groups to
the data here. We're looking at blood
FGF-21 levels. This is important because
if you well genetically knock out
FGF-21, it's a bit of a nasty shock if
you suddenly saw FGF-21 in the blood,
right? Well, hath no fear because we can
see the FGF-21 knockout leads to no
FGF-21 produced and the TG condition
there is the inducible FGF-21. So
there's a knockout of the original gene
and a maintenance of the inducible. The
WT there is the control condition, the
unmanipulated group. So they have all
their genes intact. Okay, good. The
study design worked. Now let's cut to
the main punchline and then let's get
into some additional more fascinating
findings. Do these animals live longer?
So longevity. Here we see the inducible
FGF-21 in red and the control. So less
FGF-21 in black. This is a survival
curve. So the more up and to the right
that they are, the longer that they
live. Keep in mind all else is equal. So
nutrition, exercise, and so on. We
clearly see the FGF-21 has a strong
longevity effect about a 26% increased
lifespan, which is pretty substantial.
Okay, good. I wasn't lying that this
hormone is a longevity hormone. But I
find these data actually pretty boring
because there's so much more that this
hormone does and exactly how is it
leading to these longevity effects?
Well, for one, if we look at their body
weight and body composition, the red is
the FGF-21 overexpressing group. We see
their body weight is much lower over
their lifespan than the control
condition. And beyond that, they're
leaner, indicated by reduced body fat,
as well as more lean mass, which
includes muscle. So, they live longer,
they're leaner, and more muscular. And
there's even reports of them flexing in
the mirror and winking at the married
mice's wives. Unconfirmed, though. But
what if I throw this on for you? We're
looking at total food intake and we even
see them eating more than the control.
So hold on. They're living longer,
looking better, and they get to eat
more. Sign me up. The reason for that is
because their metabolism ramps up as
seen on the right side here. It's much
higher during the waking hours. I know
it says dark there. Mice are a lot more
active at night. A lot of changes and
not tiny ones either. big changes. And
beyond that, the FGF-21 group also
experienced significant liver
protection, meaning an unhealthy liver
can accumulate fat inside the liver
cells called steattosis. But as we can
literally see, we have microscope images
of the liver sections on the right. The
white is fat. Clearly, the bottom image
indicates significantly less liver fat.
This is further confirmed by looking at
liver enzymes in the blood. These are
leaked out of stressed and dying liver
cells. So the lower the better and again
we see improvements. Also related when
testing things like insulin resistance
in this case measured by a common test
called an oral glucose tolerance test O
GTT. There in this experiment the
subject consumes a regulated amount of
glucose. So sugar and the researchers
are measuring how quickly the sugar is
then cleared from the bloodstream. So,
as we can see here, the red line returns
to baseline quickly, which indicates
reduced insulin resistance or better
insulin sensitivity as it's insulin that
generally needs to be there to clear the
blood sugar into the cells and out of
the blood. In fact, we'll return to this
because I don't want to promise
anything, but there might be some human
data on this exact same thing. No
promises, but uh you know, there's one
more thing that I want to show you.
Maybe the coolest thing and then we
should come to understand how FGF-21
actually causes these benefits. Okay,
the coolest data is here and I realize
this looks like a lot but it's simple to
read. We're looking at the genetic
differences in visceral fat, a generally
considered harmful form of fat in the
body that sticks around our organs. The
genes are on the left side. You don't
need to know them individually. Just
notice the color difference between the
control and the FGF-21 overexpressing
group TG. The more red that means
there's greater gene expression. It
seems pretty clear there's huge gene
changes between the two groups in this
fat type. So what's going on here? Well,
the researchers did a lipolysis assay,
which means that they stimulated fat
cells to release fat molecules into the
bloodstream. This tells them that if the
fat cells are behaving differently,
which they are here because under the
same conditions, the FGF-21
overexpressing group releases less fat
molecules. So, neifas or non-sterified
fatty acids that feeds into the changes
in the body fat gene signatures because
it's generally recognized that if fat
cells have a greater capacity to keep
fat inside the cell, that means there's
less spillover into surrounding organs.
Remember the liver that we looked at
earlier? Well, remember how it was
packed with fat? It's healthier for fat
molecules to be stored in fat cells than
other organs called ectopic fat. So, if
there's less release when stimulated,
that's a benefit. That of course also
affects insulin resistance and general
health because ectopic fat in our organs
reduces insulin sensitivity because
these fats interact with important
signaling enzymes inside our cells.
Beyond that they can be turned into a
harmful molecule like ceramides.
Ceramides are bioactive molecules
meaning that they actually interact with
components of our cells and change the
behavior of the cell. They have multiple
functions including positive but as
signaling molecules they can contribute
to inflammation cell death and have a
direct role in inhibiting the insulin
cascade in the cells contributing to
insulin resistance. So when we look at
the levels of ceramides inside fat
tissue here, we're again looking at the
heat map with varying size ceramide
molecules on the left side and we see
the concentration cut dramatically in
the FGF-21 condition. Sometimes half or
even a fifth of the control condition
and the reasons for that is here. These
are a bunch of camide enzymes that are
involved in the production of camides
inside the cell. So not all of them
decrease but certain key enzymes are
reduced meaning that FGF-21 reduces the
gene expression for the production of
these ceramide enzymes but that's in the
atipose tissue the fat cells themselves
there are significant reductions in
blood camides as well here the blue bars
are the FGF-21 overexpressing condition
okay so FGF-21 has widespread protective
effects and leads to some pretty
remarkable improvements movements in
health, body composition, longevity, and
more that we haven't even gone over.
Which, by the way, if you want me to
cover much more of the effects of
FGF-21, like its effects on the immune
system, its powerful interaction with
another hormone, its ability to mimic
anti-aging drugs, as well as a clever
way to increase FGF-21 naturally beyond
what we'll be going over here. I cover
all that in the extended version of this
video that you're watching. It's
included for the Physionic Insiders. If
you care about learning all the details
along with even more actionable
takeaways, check it out. The links in
the description. Oh, and that membership
also gives you access to my private
podcast, live sessions with me if you
want to discuss in more detail, weekly
articles with actionable steps,
protocols, and much more. I put a lot of
work into it. It's also a really great
community. Like I said, the link is in
the description box. Now, let's bring
this back to the human folk and how we
can take advantage of this information.
Well, as you may have noticed since I
said over and over, this particular
study was in mice and beyond that, this
was in genetically manipulated mice
known as transgenic mice. It was also in
single breed of mice. So, we should want
this to be replicated even if there are
other studies corroborating pieces of
this study. Among those studies, there
is a recent human study that actually
shows similar increases in FGF-21. We
see the FGF-21 stimulating nutrition
increases blood FGF-21 on the left side.
When the nutrition is changed, the body
no longer produces FGF-21. Don't worry,
we'll get into what that nutrition is in
a minute. But we don't actually just see
increases in FGF-21. We actually see
some of the same results that we see in
mice like here where researchers are
infusing glucose into the veins of
participants and seeing how much is
cleared out of the blood. So, it's a
different but more sensitive measure of
insulin resistance. The blue lines are
the people with the FGF-21 in their
blood. And we can see there's more
glucose infusion needed, meaning that
more is cleared out of the tissues, a
strong sign of insulin sensitivity. That
all is technically still associative
data. But that study in humans also
showed other evidence to create a direct
link, not just an association. I'll link
my analysis in the description because
there are other things that were similar
between the human data and the mouse
data that I won't uh relitigate here.
So, how do we increase FGF-21 in
ourselves? Well, it's actually extremely
simple. Reduce your protein intake. Yep.
The human study that I referenced did
only that. They just reduced protein
intake to 9% of total calories, which is
quite low, but still well above levels
indicated to be unsafe as it meets all
of the necessary amino acid
requirements. Of course, that's also
dependent on the protein source. But
we're assuming quality complete protein
sources. That said, there are a few
cautions that I should outline here.
One, the human study was in young,
healthy men who did not exercise. Since
protein requirements change with
activity, it's unknown if it's viable
for people who exercise intensely,
especially over the long term. Two, as
we age into our 60s and beyond, our
protein requirements tend to increase.
So, it may be more detrimental than
beneficial to reduce protein that low.
We don't know. However, even in the
study that we're going over, old mice
did not experience as noticeable an
increase in metabolism shown here side
by side with the young mice that we
looked at over earlier. You can see the
increase in energy expenditure. So,
metabolism is blunted. But if you're
thinking that FGF-21 has no effect in
those older, then think again because
they still experience the insulin
sensitivity benefits similar to the
young. So the FGF-21 is still causing
some positive effects. Regardless, it
would be good to have specific
longerterm human studies in older
individuals to see if the benefits are
going to outweigh the cost. So potential
lean mass loss as one example. If you're
a physionic insider, I'm going to go
into that in more depth, including some
alternatives if interested. Okay. So to
button this up, FGF-21 is a hormone
that's secreted by many cells of the
body. And there is preliminary data
indicating that it extends lifespan but
also improves body weight, body
composition, and insulin sensitivity
along with protecting our organs from
developing fat inside them. Short-term
human studies indicate that consuming a
low but still viable protein diet of 9%
of total calories stimulates FGF-21 in
our body. I would like to see more human
studies, especially in older folks, but
there's a lot of remarkable effects in
humans that I didn't cover, which you
can find right here. I cover more on the
effects of FGF-21 in humans. Thanks for
nerding out with me, and I'll catch you
later. Bye.